Guide to the Paul Novick / Sholem Asch Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Paul Novick papers relating to Sholem Asch
1943-1963
GEN MSS 117
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.5
(4 boxes)
Collection consists of correspondence, writings, articles and notes by and about Sholem Asch gathered by Paul Novick, editor of the only paper willing to publish him at the height of the controversy over his trilogy, Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene, 1939), Der Sheliekh (The Apostle, 1943), and Meri (Mary, 1949). Jewish leaders accused Asch of teaching conversion to Christianity, a charge that Asch emphatically denied. Asch's writings reflect his concern for the Jews in Europe during and after the second World War.
Noṿiḳ, P., 1891-
Asch, Sholem, 1880-1957
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Charles Apfelbaum on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1992.
Conditions Governing Access
Restricted Fragile Papers in boxes 3 and 4 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files. For more information consult with Access Services.
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings, articles and notes by and about Sholem Asch gathered by Paul Novick, editor of the Morgen Frayhayt (Morning Freedom), a Communist Party Yiddish newspaper in New York, the only newspaper willing to publish him at the height of the controversy over his trilogy, Der Man fun Notseres (The Nazarene) (1939), Der Sheliekh (The Apostle) (1943), and Meri (Mary) (1949). Jewish leaders accused Asch of teaching conversion to Christianity, a charge that Asch emphatically denied. The correspondence between Asch and Novick make up a large part of the collection.
The Correspondence consists of letters between Asch and Novick at a time when, due to ill health, Asch was advised by his physician not to defend his controversial works in the press. These letters document Asch's reaction to the controversy. Novick's letters are represented by carbon copies. A small section of other letters, mostly to and from Novick about Asch's works, is filed at the end of the series.
The Writings consist of essays by Asch, divided into one section of complete works, and one of incomplete and untitled works. The essays are organized alphabetically by transliterated Yiddish with the English translation appearing in parentheses. The incomplete works have been summarized. The miscellaneous section contains works about Asch, probably written by Novick. Most of the articles have been placed in restricted fragile papers, and reference photocopies have been supplied. In two cases, only the article about Asch was photocopied, and the rest of the paper itself may be consulted in restricted fragile papers.
Man fun Natseres. Yiddish. 1939; Médicament, éthique et réalité industrielle (Series). Yiddish. 1949; Sheliekh. Yiddish. 1943; Authors, Yiddish -- United States -- Archives; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945) -- Poland; Morgn-frayhayṭ; Noṿiḳ, P., 1891-; Sholem Asch, 1880-1957
- Box and Folder List
  - Correspondence
    - Between Asch and Novick
      - Aug-Oct, Dec, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
      - Jan-Dec, n.d., 1944 (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
      - Jan-Dec, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Jan-Apr, n.d., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
      - Feb-Oct, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Jan-Oct, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Jul (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Other Correspondence
      - Asch to Mr. Perelman of the Morning Freiheit, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Committee of Jewish Writers and Artists, 1944 Jan 19 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Between Novick and G. P. Putnam's Sons, 1948 Feb-Oct (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Yale University Press to Novick, 1945 Jan 16 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Writings
    - Essays
      - "Eyner fun Dray Milyon" (One in Three Million) typescript, corrected, 1945 Mar (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - "Farlozt Aykh auf di Boyes" (Rely on the "Boys[?]) holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - "Far Yedn Geeynigten Aden [?]--a Bombe--Daytschland" (For Every United [?] --a Bomb--Germany) holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - "Fir Brider Zenen Mir Geven" (We Were Four Brothers) holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - "Peysekhdiker Gedanken" (Passover Thoughts) typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - "Varshe: A fantastish motiv far a [?]" (Warsaw: A fantasy motif for [?]) holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - "Der Yidisher Pabyedanavtsar in Zayn Senat" (The Jewish Pabyedanavtsar [?] in his Senate) holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - "A Yidish Kind in Shanos 5695: Gevidmet di Kinder in Poylen" (A Jewish Child in the Year 1944/45) holograph, corrected (Box 1, Folder 28)
        Scope and Contents
        With leaf of instructions to publisher
      - "Zey Hobn Nisht Keyn Gloybn in Sotsializm" (They Have No Belief in Socialism)
        - Holograph, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Early typescript draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - Later typescript draft, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - "Zolen di Toyte Begrobn di Toyte" (Let the Dead Bury the Dead) holograph, corrected, 1944 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Untitled and incomplete essays
      - Untitled essay beginning "Dem tog hot Got geshafn" (God created the day...), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      - Untitled essay beginning "Ven a ideal aroysgerufn durch noyt un umgezikhtigkayt [?] ferfelt oystsufirn zayn misie far welkhn tsvek er iz bashtimt...." (When an ideal called forth by need and lack of foresight [?] fails to accomplish its mission for which purpose it is designated....), 1944 Feb 4 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      - Untitled essay of personal reflections, holograph, corrected, c. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Article about the English Labour Party, typescript, corrected, fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
      - Article discussing his life and the Asch-Rabinowitz Collection at Yale, typescript, corrected, fragment (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Condemnation of Abraham Kahn, typescript, corrected, fragment (Box 1, Folder 38)
      - Forward 's preface to the "Shtetl", fragment, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 39)
      - Fragments, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Asch Miscellany
      - Articles, 1943-63, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41-50)
      - Eulogies, 1957, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Notes about, 1943, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Unidentified fragments, 1943-45, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Restricted Fragile Papers
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted Fragile Papers in Boxes 3-4 may be consulted only with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies for reference use have been substituted in the main files.
    - Box 2, folder 42 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Box 2, folder 43 (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Box 2, folder 44 (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - Box 2, folder 45 (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - Box 2, folder 46 (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Box 2, folder 47 (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - Box 2, folder 47 (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Box 2, folder 48 (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Box 2, folder 49 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - Box 2, folder 49 (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Box 2, folder 50 (Box 4, Folder 64)